SHANTANOO SINHA

Chicago, IL • (224) 282-5081 • shantanoo.sinha@gmail.com • linkedin.com/in/shantanoo-sinha github.com/shantanoo-sinha • https://shantanoo-sinha.github.io/

SUMMARY

Team player with Masters degree in Computer Science & 9 years of software development experience seeking an opportunity as a Software Engineer. Offering a working knowledge of software development, algorithms, data structures, networks, & databases.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer

CME Group, Chicago, USA

May 2020 - Present

- Migrated legacy application logic written in PL/SQL to Java rest microservices using Java, Spring Boot, Hibernate, JUnit & Mockito
- Maintained & enhanced internal web application using C#, .Net MVC, MSSQL, ¡Query, SignalR, Excel libraries
- Created automated testing regression suite in C#, .Net MVC using MSTest reducing manual testing by over 70%

Student Assistant

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, USA

September 2019 – May 2020

- Provided technical assistance to students, faculty, staff, tenants, guests, and visitors with the campus technologies
- Troubleshooted software applications, computers, mobile devices, printers, phones AV, printer & plotter issues

Software Engineer

IHS Markit, Noida, India

July 2015 – August 2019

- Devised microservices based architecture using Java, SpringBoot, Hibernate & REST API for the distribution of data to clients
- Implemented a CLI application in Java, HTMLUnit to web-scrape & download 1000+ monthly reports thus saving manual efforts
- Remodeled the UI using Angular 6, Typescript, JavaScript & Bootstrap and improved application performance over 50%
- Reduced application deployment time up to 80% by writing Puppet manifests for 50+ production applications
- Recognized with 'Star Award' & 'Most Valuable Player' award for top performance across the organization

Software Engineer

Tata Consultancy Services, India

December 2011 – July 2015

- Led, supervised technical direction, mentoring and training for a team of 8 software developers
- Developed Timesheet entry & Claim-reimbursement modules using Java, Struts, jQuery, JavaScript & MySQL
- Automated build and deployment by building a generic automated CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins, GitLab & Docker
- Analyzed and optimized complex slow running SQL queries and reduced the running time by 30%
- Awarded 'Star of the Learner's Group' award in a batch of 40 trainees

Software Developer Intern

Sahara India Limited, Lucknow, India

July 2010 – August 2010

- Coded an internal web application tool for Online Letter Processing System using ASP.Net, C#, MS SQL to store, forward & review official documents electronically and automate management of letters
- Programmed archival process and designed a daily end-of-day batch job to archive old data and files

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Peer to Peer File Sharing (Java, RMI, Multi-thread, Git, Vagrant, Fedora) Source Code

- Designed a Napster style & decentralized Gnutella style P2P file sharing applications using Java, RMI & multithreading
- Implemented RSA asymmetric cryptography without using in-built APIs for network traffic encryption and improving data security

Bigdata Analysis of Yelp Dataset (Hadoop, Spark, Hive, Pig, Python, Tableau) Source Code

- Analyzed <u>Yelp dataset</u> by creating a data pipeline in Hadoop to import the data in HDFS and Apache Hive
- Transformed the data using Spark & Pig and presented dashboards using Tableau Desktop visualizations

Database Management System (C, Git, Linux) Source Code

• Implemented a small Database Management System in C with a disk-based B+ tree index structure & Buffer Pool implementation

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Flixster (Java, Android, Async HTTP, YouTube Player View, Glide) Source Code

• Designed Flixster android app using Java for users to browse movies from the The Movie Database API and watch movie trailers

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Java
- PL/SQL

JPA

- ĮL
- REST Microservices
- jQuery | JavaScript
- GitLab CI/CD | Jenkins

- Android (Java)
- Spring Boot
- Hazelcast Caching
- Bootstrap
- Maven

- C#
- ASP.Net MVC
- Junit | Mockito
- Git | SVN

- Python
- Hibernate
- Angular
- Puppet
- Markit (CADIS) EDM

EDUCATION

Master of Science - Computer Science
Bachelor of Technology - Information Technology

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago Gautam Buddh Technical University, India 3.6/4.0

August 2019 - May 2021

3.0/4.0

August 2007 - July 2011